I think we might as well get started. It's 7PM
time to call the regular meeting of the Andover
Inland Wetlands and Water Crisis Commission to order.
I see by the Zoom screen
that, in addition to myself,
Commissioners Larson
and Monroe are present, as well as Agent Wagner
and interested members of the public and our
devoted Clerk, Abby.
So,
item three on the agenda, changes in order to agenda. Actually, I'd like to add to the agenda
an item 8B,
which would be
a consideration
of scheduling a hearing
for
adoption
of revised
regulations.
This is something that's been in the works for a while. So again, 8B,
hearing
for
revision of regulations.
If there are no objections, we can adopt that by unanimous consent.
Seeing none, we'll move on to
approval
of minutes.
We have first the minutes for
12/06/2021,
and I'll first ask commissioners
if they have any
edits or revisions
or additions to the minutes as
distributed?
I had none.
>> William?
Chair Elliott, I I think there was a a mistake with the dates
and the jurisdictional
of
it was, like, January 11
and January 18, but I think that was supposed to be December 11 and December 18.
>> That would have been correct.
Because we actually had the sidewalk
on the eleventh and we were considering those two dates, December eleventh
and eighteenth.
Good catch.
I did notice in the others
present of
the minutes,
You had listed
Marci Minor as present. Actually, was Jeff Minor. He was just hiding behind
Marci's avatar,
the way Bill does sometimes too.
Yeah,
all the time.
>> She's got you relabeled on our screen, so we know who it Okay.
Okay,
so any other additions or corrections?
In that case, I'll move to adopt
the to approve the minutes as revised
and
ask for I will do it by roll call.
Commissioner Larson?
Aye.
Aye. Commissioner Monroe.
>> I vote aye as well. So the motion carries three-zero-zero.
Next,
minutes for the special meeting, SiteWalk,
on,
as Commissioner noted,
on Saturday, December 11.
Again,
I will move
to approve
and ask for
comments,
revisions,
etc.
Nothing.
>> Okay,
seeing no
and hearing no comments, I'll ask him for a vote.
Commissioner Larson.
Aye.
Commissioner Monroe.
Aye. I vote aye. It's again 300
to approve.
Okay, next item public comment for
interested members of the public who don't have something on the agenda.
Okay,
seeing no hands raised, I will
move on to
Item six, old business.
So we have permits
and may be able to take action.
So these are pending
permits that we have received
at a previous meeting.
The first is application number 2126
for
work to be done at Number 1 Lakeside Drive.
See applicant Todd Perkins is on the line. Yes, sir. And
I will ask if there have been any
updates
to the application
since we received it.
>> I almost stopped by. Two individuals from Alma stopped by, and they did approve my project. And I received an email from them, and I forwarded it on to you guys, so you should have that.
I think it was a PDF, but I can't be sure. It was a few weeks back, three weeks maybe.
>> Right, I do have a copy of that
approval email.
I'm pulling it up just now.
Yeah, approval of the request.
Contingent,
this is an interesting one, contingent on the IWWC
accepting
the mortar proposed for use in the application.
For the what did it say? It says
>> contingent on the IWWC
accepting the mortar proposed
for use in the application. Oh, Now syntactically, that's a very interesting statement. I don't know that any mortar
was actually applied to the document,
and I think that they are actually asking us to approve the use of mortar
and not a brand of mortar or a type of mortar.
>> No, I can tell you the brand. I've already purchased
Exactly. I figured out. Yeah. And they
>> they wanted to see the mortar, and it it I had it wrapped up about six times in tarp.
And so we spent considerable time unwrapping it so they could see that it's sacchrete.
And they thought that that would be okay, but they weren't sure. And they went back and they had their powwow and they decided that it was fine.
And they sent me what I sent you.
It was mortared before,
so it's not new.
And, I think they even commented further that it would be,
approved because of my proximity to Cheney Brook that without it,
I'm doomed to do this all over again, which I'd rather not live to see.
>> Well, I I take your point there. It's and and, yeah, I recall about the
erosion
due to the outflow from Chaney Brook.
I'll ask
Commissioners Larson or Monroe if they have any questions or comments about the
application.
>> The only question I had was
from a
correctness
and consistency
of the applications.
As I looked through 580
Lake Road today, I was reminded that there's this DEEP
form
that's required with each application.
And I don't know that I've seen a lot of those lately, and so my question is,
shouldn't that be part of the application and it needs to be submitted to the state?
>> It's here. They aren't posted on the website because.
But they're they're usually completed
when the application comes in.
I have I have this
one right here.
>> Okay. That sounds good. As long as we're covered on that.
I wanted to comment. I didn't
see
the kind of detail that we're used to
getting
in previous
lake wall applications,
especially with respect to the restacked
part of it, not the mortared portion,
although it does
apply in some ways to the mortared portion.
Typically, the stack walls will have a silt barrier,
know, a geotextile
and or gravel
backings
the wall
to reduce
the potential for
intrusion of silt into the lake.
Also,
don't see the
construction
erosion control and lake bed protection.
That I've
seen in previous applications,
usually the contractor
will
provide
information
about how they intend to protect the lake bed while they're working on it,
working on the outside face of the wall,
how they will prevent any erosion
that would occur as a result of soil disturbances.
I think that's particularly important here because
we noted in the photographs
that
there was soil
already
placed
on-site.
And in your application, you mentioned needing to fill
areas that had been eroded
along with the wall collapse.
So
>> I'll
either ask or we would either have to postpone
consideration or else get some assurance
that
those materials can be provided,
I would say, to agent Wagner's and our satisfaction,
prior to the beginning of construction.
>> Okay. To address your introduction with this comment,
I don't know what you're accustomed to,
but I know what you've asked for, and I've provided it. So has Alma.
And if I don't get approval tonight,
I'll scrap the project and my yard will continue to bleed into the lake.
>> Can I
can I add something? This is the agent Wagner.
Was just this project is
a little bit different than the previous ones.
Because
there's no
like the the previous ones that we've approved recently,
they required excavation,
and then they would install the
the gravel behind it. They would, like, totally rebuild the wall. Whereas this one,
they're just restacking the existing wall. It's not as
as involved as a project.
So
in order, you know, if you're going to
excavate behind it, put gravel, filter fabric, I mean, that would totally change the nature of the project where this one was more of a simple
restacking the wall and remorting it, not totally
rebuilding it from scratch in the same same location,
which was
kind of the other ones.
So, you
could, you
could, know, you could add as a
into the motion to approve it, you could add the conditions that.
Road and proper erosion controls
would would be installed to protect the lake.
Know, you could do that, rather than postpone the
>> Yeah. No. I'd
rather not postpone it. But again,
I
think that those are
the erosion control and lake bed protection during construction activity, even though they're lightweight
and,
you know, but the others have not involved equipment either.
But as you say, Agent Wagner, we have a situation where it's
a lower impact
activity.
As I say, still, do have that
soil that's already in place
that would be subject to erosion during the construction project
and
want some assurance
that
there will be precautions
taken to mitigate
that
possibility.
>> Yeah. That's why it's like, if if I could make a suggestion, you could just make a motion to approve it on the condition that,
you know, a a silt fence or or whatever you would like, silt fence, a hay bale
Would be installed between the.
The wall reconstruction project and the lake bed during the during
work.
>> Right now you will be.
How shall I say present at the initiation,
right? Who may have a chance to
talk to the contractor?
I mean, that's a typical condition that you're going to be.
>> No, I don't think it is.
Usually not. I usually get notified when the work gets started.
>> Right, okay, so notice. And then I can show Not necessarily.
>> I can drive by it. I don't I don't spend enough time here to to be present for every for
everything.
>> Right. No, I I was I'm sorry. I misspoke. You you're right. This notification
>> that's required. Yeah. Yeah. That is that's part of the standard condition that are issued with our permit.
Okay, any commissioners want to weigh in on this?
>> But I would like to ask, you know,
from what I saw of the wall that is being reworked,
it looked to me like there were,
I guess my question is how many rocks are you actually looking to put back up in cement? It looked like
from what I could see at a distance, the wall was in pretty good shape. It just had
a couple of rocks that had fallen down.
When did you look at it?
It was probably
a couple weeks ago.
It's already been restocked.
>> Okay. And
I guess that's why it looked in pretty good shape.
>> Well, that's good to hear. They're doing a good job,
but I can't continue with this work until I I have approval from your committee.
>> Right.
And
if we're getting Vice Chair, Chairman Ella sure, yeah.
>> I share your concern about, you know, normally we see the crushed stone with the some kind of fabric behind there to prevent the erosion.
And
I certainly would have preferred
to see that. I thought
that
there was so little work on the wall that
that wasn't that much of a concern to me this time, but it sounds like the wall was in worse shape and it's
been repaired already, I guess.
Should have pictures of it before it was restocked.
>> Right,
and
it was definitely tumbled down. It was hard to tell exactly the condition. The mortared portion,
which I guess adjoins your block,
and that's the portion that I take it remains to be worked on
to,
you know, either that or we've really gotten our socks on over our shoes here
in terms of doing the work before the permit is issued.
So
I
guess I could entertain a motion to approve the
application,
again, contingent on satisfactory
erosion control
for and lake bed production
during the
construction activities,
and
that
agent Wagner will be afforded an opportunity
by notification
of the
initiation of that work.
>> Okay, so is this another addendum
to my application that I'll need to submit?
>> I think you could
submit it. Yeah, it would be good if you could submit it for the record.
And again,
I don't think we have to
revisit the application in another meeting. We can
give you a contingent approval,
knowing that conditions are currently favorable for getting the work done
other than being cold.
The lake is down,
and, you know, you have access,
to the lakeshore.
>> Right. The access is, of course, important. I I have absolutely zero interest in this guy
starting work in this kind of weather
because I have concern about how the mortar might set up.
As eager as he may be to get started, I won't permit it until it's above freezing.
Right.
>> So
I guess I need definition
on
what it is that you meet. Like, somebody mentioned hay bales. What is it that you want me to do
to
enable this work to proceed once it's not seven degrees outside? Outside.
>> Right. Again, it's a question of getting the contractor
to supply
information about what he would do to
avoid erosion
and lake bed disturbance
during the construction activities.
>> Can I
ask you to clarify something? I'm
of the impression that all the restacking has been done. The only thing that's left is to
apply the mortar. Is that correct?
That is correct.
>> Okay.
To me, that seems
like there's pretty low
risk of erosion from that point, like the risk, the highest risk would have been
when the rocks were being stacked, not when the
mortar is being put on. So I think the standard conditions of providing appropriate
erosion control that are issued with every permit should suffice for that kind of activity.
Okay.
Did
I mean, that's that's the commission's decision.
K. Any comments
from commissioners Larson or Monroe?
>> Well, I agree with the the low probability of the need for the hay bales in that. I guess I'll go back now.
I misunderstood
the whole mortar concept.
I thought the mortar would be put between the rocks as the wall was rebuilt
to hold the rocks in place. I guess I
miss
I don't have the right idea there. It looks like we're putting a smooth concrete face on the water side of the wall. Is that what the plan is now? No, sir.
>> I I don't do this kind of work, so I I don't know the technical terminology.
But
he's he restocked the walls
and told me he was going to
fit mortar
than within the stones,
I guess,
for lack of a better word, kind of a packet in there,
and that would,
that would keep the stones in place for a very long time.
>> And, again, that was only for a portion of the wall, if I'm if I'm
The the mortar portion
of the wall.
>> He was planning to put the mortar on the entire length of the wall.
With particular
concentration
on the part of my wall that
bends
from lakeside up towards
my property
and is one of the first points of contact
to,
the rushing waters from from Cheney.
And those waters are not rushing all the time. But as you know, we've had several storms within just the past year
that started this whole ball rolling.
So
in an effort to avoid that in the future.
>> Okay.
I'm sorry. Just quickly reviewing the application.
Because it speaks to of of preexisting
stone to be placed back and former mortar replaced.
Again,
the
photographs
that, accompanied the application,
wasn't
clear that the entire
wall had been
mortared,
And so
I took it to,
again, apply only to a portion of the wall that,
was mortared at the at the time of the application
and, again, approximate to the doc. Okay.
So
where we stand now seems to me there's a little confusion,
but
the
gist of it is you've restacked the wall. The only thing that remains to be done pending
favorable weather conditions
is to apply mortar
pocket in to hold the stones in place.
>> On the face of the wall, yes. And and I guess probably the top of it too.
But I mean,
the goal is the effort is to leave the stone
appearance of the wall because it's far more attractive than just a big concrete wall,
much like the dam, which is
perfect the way it is. It's necessary.
But,
you know, aesthetically,
what our aim was to do is to just secure the stones with
some mortar
and
leave much of the stones
intact so that that's what's visible.
>> Okay. And leave the impression of a drywall
construction. Right. Okay. Right.
Okay. And again, as we said, we have the
situation of the
standard conditions
allowing for,
well, requiring
erosion control.
And again, in this case, lake bed production is what we're really left with.
And it sounds like it's pretty low impact activity
since there's no
excavation
required.
So,
I guess I'll go along with Agent Wagner and
that the standard conditions,
that apply to our applications,
to approve the applications,
will suffice,
in this case.
Thank you.
And
again, asking for any further comments from commissioners.
>> So I guess at this point, you know, my my question would be,
and again,
Mr. Perkins
probably isn't
familiar with what other folks around the lake have done,
but every other wall that's been rebuilt
has had the contractor come in to brief us on the plan and it's had a plan that's had crushed stone and fabric behind
the stone wall to prevent the washing away of the
soil
that we saw in this case.
I very much want to protect the lake and prevent that
soil from going in again. My question is, why
would we not put the crushed stone in the fabric behind
the wall as part of the repair that we did?
Alright. Is that a question you've directed to me?
Yes.
>> I'm I'm I'm not a contractor or a mason.
I I suspect that
the wall being a 100 years old
and having fallen about
maybe a third of it, maybe not that much
into the lake,
having been restacked and then packed with mortar
is,
what I've been led to believe
would be sufficient to preventing
any kind of erosion from my property entering the lake further.
Although, they I don't imagine there's anything that would guarantee that a 100%.
So
>> I don't know why it's not now you can't even give them now.
That's what I was
What's that?
Joe, did that response
satisfy your question?
>> Yes and no. I guess, know, we
haven't voted yet, but I would like to add a conditional approval
of if the silt
gets washed out from behind the wall again,
that the
more robust repair
of putting crushed stone in a fabric liner
to prevent the washout of soil
be done at the next repair.
>> Which hopefully there won't be.
Okay, so I hope not.
Okay,
>> I
don't remember now if I actually made a motion,
>> but if I haven't, I will make a motion. You said you were prepared to, but then you offered it Right. Back to your
>> Okay, so I'll make a motion that we approve this
application,
again, with standard conditions and understanding
that
the
desirable,
if further
occurrences
warrant,
that additional steps should be taken
to prevent
erosion
from the site.
Okay.
Is that an adequate statement for you, Jud?
Yes.
>> Okay,
and
William, do you have any further
comments?
No. I'll
ask for a vote on the motion. Oh, did I get a second to the motion?
I'll second it. Second. Okay, Monroe seconds.
>> So the motion is on the floor. Again, I'll ask for a vote
by roll call. Commissioner Larson?
Aye.
>> Commissioner Monroe?
And Chair Elliott also vote aye.
So, the motion is approved, and the permit is approved.
Again, please be in contact with
Agent Wagner
as you proceed towards getting this
work
done
to make sure that he's informed of progress.
Will do. Thank you very much, gentlemen.
>> Okay.
Moving on then. And by the way, you're free. You're excused from the meeting if I
>> sit around for the rest of day. Thank you. Good night. Okay.
>> Okay. So next we have application
from Gary McCullough, who I see is on the call,
at 3 Lakeside Drive originally
to
put sand
on a,
quote beach area
at their waterfront,
and
to,
again originally
to reconstruct
an existing
deck
or dock, I should say.
Now, there have been some
changes
occurring since that application
was originally received.
The
commission
was in receipt of a copy of a letter
to Mr. McCullough regarding
the
sand that had been placed on the lake bed,
saying that that was not a permitted use,
that they would require
that that sand would be removed.
Secondly,
we
received a modification
of the application
to,
instead of creating a sand beach,
to
build a retaining wall,
rebuild perhaps a retaining wall
so that
essentially a sandbox
or
beach like area
could be created,
but with erosion control
and the remainder of the
lake frontage
to be
converted to a lawn.
We haven't seen any plans,
as I'm aware of, for the replacement
of the dock, but we are in receipt of a letter
from, again, Andover Lake Management Association to the effect that they're not really concerned
about
removal
of
the old dock.
Although, again, it would still be an
activity that requires,
a wetlands permit.
Agent Wagner,
do you have anything further to comment on
the,
application
as
your communications?
>> Yeah. I don't. And then I just, I worked with
Gary to kinda come up with a
different application. We had
he had received a a letter from Alma, you know, that that stated that they didn't want the sand
below the high watermark on the Alma property.
And then he
came up with the moving of sand behind the wall, which is a
it's a pretty good alternative, I feel like,
to eliminating
erosion into the lake and then restoring that area that the beach used to exist that.
And there is a
description like a revised description of the project that's
online.
It's posted under
under as dated
January 10, the description of proposed project that explains what
what the revised application
entails.
So the doc
isn't gonna it's just gonna get removed,
which was okayed by Alma. They said they don't involve themselves in removing docs, just installing a new one.
But that they would have to review the
proposed stonewall reconstruction.
>> Yeah.
Yeah,
this is Gary. So
yeah, thanks agent Wagner for the help and
this was kind of a learning process for me.
And
so I
would like
to communicate as far as this meeting goes,
what I'd like to be able to do is just gather the additional information that's going to be needed. Like I learned a lot about what needs to be done with a stone wall
with what Todd has
been going through.
So I can learn from that
and get a more detailed plan around that stone wall
moving forward of course.
So we may need to extend this
application
because I've really adjusted the plan dramatically.
And just for the record too,
the
beach area,
the existing beach area,
there was already sand there as well as sand into the water.
I had, because the lake was down, thought I was doing okay.
I thought that was okay to do. I've learned differently.
I've agreed to remove that sand
that was put down.
And then I think it would be a good idea to
grow the lawn or grow the grass and natural stuff back down into the water.
And then where there's
a diagram there that shows the existing wall or what remains of an existing wall
that would be rebuilt much the same way that Todd did. But I think what we'll do is
reinforce
that
shore facing or land facing side of that wall
with
approved
gravel.
And
I think you mentioned some
sort of fabric or something like that. So
that's my vision.
Long way from completing the vision but again looking for
your guys'
input so that the next time through the detail is there so
we can make progress.
Does that make sense?
>> Yeah, it makes sense to me. By the by the way, the sand on the beach
is naturally occurring. It's a glacial formation
and esker.
Well, was
thought that we left it there. Yeah, yeah, probably, but that's why the beach is where it is. Yeah,
>> when I was at town hall, we were looking at
records
of permits
in the past
and there was approved
permits
back in the early 2000s,
I think.
Joe may know the dates, but there was pictures of sand being
brought down there.
>> So that was They replenish had
the natural.
But anyway, that's Yeah, on the that was my initial
>> desire was to replenish
until,
as people
have told me, things have changed and there's a lot more focus, and I understand that.
So I'm just trying to play within the rules.
>> Okay, well, thanks for that consideration.
I think that,
yeah, you've touched
on the main points, and I think working with Agent Binder to
refine the plans,
and
if
you're going to be working with a contractor,
certainly getting them to provide the kind of detail
that we're accustomed to seeing in
lake wall applications.
Agent Wagner had shared with me some
recommendations,
I believe it was from New Hampshire,
that were
relevant to, and some work examples for
lakeshore
improvements,
the
sort you're talking about,
and how to create a beach
on a lake,
and using a retaining wall to create a level area and reduce
erosion
was one of the
suggestions that was made in that publication.
So, it seems like you're on the right track.
And again,
a contractor
would be able to provide a good deal of detail about
lake bed protection and erosion
mitigation
during any kind of construction process. Yeah. Yep.
Okay,
members of the Commission, I'll ask for comments,
suggestions.
>> Well, I certainly appreciate the applicant's
desire to do the right thing.
I know from my own experience how little I knew about living on a lake and wetlands rules until I got on the Wetlands Commission
and started learning all that.
The one piece,
and I do think the plan
sounds conceptually
much better than the current plan. I guess the question I'm wrestling with
is
one of the alternatives to be considered would be the
removal
of the sand. And I know that's typical,
but
why
should it be
good for the lake to, yeah, don't know how much sand you brought in. It looks like a pretty extensive amount that,
why even have that sand there?
Sometimes,
>> you know, it's just like you've going in and calling with literal stupid.
>> Question addressed to the applicant, so. Yeah, yeah, I just heard somebody else talking. I I maybe.
>> Well, we're getting some cross talk from.
Doing unmuted mic here.
Why not unmute myself there?
>> Yeah.
Okay,
so
yeah, there was.
It was about 10 yards.
Of sand brought in.
And.
As
far as removing it, yeah, I mean I'm going to move probably five back up and
some of the other uses I have for the sand is there's a there's
stone deck up by the house
past 200 feet.
And
so to to kind of reseat some of that
and some other
work in the front of the property.
So I may use it for that, but I don't have specific plans, but I
do plan on moving
much of that sand back up
towards the
sheds,
200 feet away from the
high watermark.
So, and then, so the purpose
for the sand
is aesthetic,
one. Two,
you know, whether it matters or not, I mean, kind of grew up as a child on Crystal Lake and my grandparents had a place and they had a sandy beach. I got grandkids now and I'd love to share some of that experience with them,
even though it's not a beach that flows into the water, it's it's still a beach by the water and we can take our boats out and
paddle boat, you know, paddle boat and
that kind of stuff. So it's kind of, that's,
ask me why, that's why.
>> Chairman Elliot, I would like to make a motion that we schedule a site visit because the new
pictures that I saw online
didn't really give me the perspective.
Thought
all the sand was dumped into the lake bed. I didn't know there was an existing beach back there and
it would just help clarify,
at least in my mind, coming up with the right decision
on the application.
>> Yeah.
Yeah, I'm
I'm okay with that. I mean, you'll see that
there's a couple of yards in the in the water.
I talked to the guy and
he was actually
he wanted to move it out today. I says
you're nuts.
But he's eager to move that sand and we're just going to move it up above
from the waterline or above the waterline.
And then where it goes from there depends on what we decide to do.
Right? So that's
before I start moving
it around anywhere,
I'd like to just have,
we're all in consensus with
what's doable.
And
then
again I can I can
you know parcel some of the sand over there and move the rest back and if we have to give it to the fire department make sandbags out of it and I'm probably will be okay with that too?
>> Okay, so
I concur with Commissioner Larson in that a site
visit
would be desirable in this case, because there seem to be a lot of moving parts
in this application,
and it's been revised,
as it were, on the fly.
The
question would be when we could schedule
that
for
Well, it's got to be suitable weather. I'm not going to even consider this coming Saturday.
Typically, we have our sitewalks on Saturday mornings at 09:00.
And again, just like with mortaring the wall at,
let's see, at number one, Lakeside, we've got to, at the other application,
we have to have above freezing weather, I think, at least for this
exercise.
So, it's hard to look out at the calendar and
pick a date
with the current conditions,
but I suppose we could at least tentatively
schedule
a sidewalk
prior to our next regular meeting,
which will be on, what, February 6.
So,
any suggestions about time there from
commissioners?
I'm open.
Ain't going anywhere.
>> Well,
I think 09:00 always works well for us. My question would be should we tentatively schedule it for the January 22,
so if the weather's horrible,
we have the twenty ninth available to us before we come to the next meeting? Yeah, well, we'd actually have the twenty ninth and the fifth,
>> February 5, because our the first Monday
and
Yep, okay, my mistake. Yep, looking at the calendar. But yeah, I think that would be good. Why don't we pencil in a meeting
for February 22?
Again, a special meeting
February 22, 9AM
for a sidewalk.
January.
Okay.
>> Yeah.
So
I'm I'm in the process of selling my home
in
Vernon.
I have not yet
actually moved in
to
3 Lakeside.
And I
had some plans for actually moving. I got my brother in laws or son in laws, whoever the heck they are. Oh, no. Truck trucks to do some moving.
We could make the twenty second work.
The closing has just been moved out to the February 4.
So I'm going to be
pretty. So I doubt obviously want to be there for your site walk through.
So you're saying the January
22.
Right, that would be the the the earliest opportunity
>> and but then we'd have a contingency for the twenty ninth.
Exactly.
Okay, so.
Let's let's shoot for that and and I I just like to have the option of if with weather and my closing date I have to have everything out of the house and coordinating that I may request that we may move it out even further,
but.
>> Yeah, we can work with that. I'm sure we can work with that all right.
Okay,
>> So
in between now and then,
I did
look at the Alma website and there is a more detailed form
that they require for
building a wall or repairing a wall.
And there's some detail there,
which I need to
look through and,
you know, fill that out.
So
what is the purpose of the walkthrough? Is it to determine whether
this is
feasible at the level that we're talking about now or?
>> It's again,
we call it a sidewalk simply because we were looking to get a physical
sense
of the location
so that we can see how the
work that's proposed
fits
into,
you know, the existing conditions and what
it would do
to
the site and its potential impact,
in this case, on the water course and overlay.
>> Yeah,
Okay.
And then from there, then we'd be able to
figure out whether or not the
rock wall is
Rebuilding that
I mean Joe took a look at the the wall. I don't know. We had some pictures too. I don't know if we want to spend some time.
Looking at that or Joe can
provide a little bit of
insight into what
he saw,
whether that's a value at this meeting. Don't know, I'm just throwing that out.
>> Yeah,
I had a look at the pictures, and they do certainly
provide
a good view,
but
it's
sometimes hard to grasp the full, how should I say, three-dimensional,
characteristics.
>> Oh, yeah, throw a little snow on top of it and kind of
gloomy weather. Yeah, I get it.
>> So, I agree with Commissioner
Larson that
a sidewalk would be in order here,
and it looks like we're all okay with, again, we're scheduling the twenty second to do that,
and we have
further discussion.
And let's give you more time to
look at those ALMA
regulations
and consider
just exactly how you want to approach
the
project in terms of getting,
you know, what you're looking for aesthetically
and functionally.
Yeah. Well, again, satisfying
requirements
to
mitigate
any potential
for sedimentation
and impact
on the lake.
Yeah.
>> All right. Just one more question.
You had mentioned the New Hampshire,
you know, kind of blueprint, if you will, for
designing a beach at a lake
site.
So could I consider that something that,
I mean, do do you and the other commissioners are are familiar with that and would say, yeah, that's if you follow that,
you know, blueprint,
that would be a a good a good starting point? Or is there any concerns with what is stated in in that document?
>> Okay, I'm only familiar with it recently.
Agent Wagner shared it with me after
he was,
after we started working on your application.
And
I don't think we could
say off the top of our heads. I don't know if the other commissioners have even seen this
document,
so I wouldn't want to say that it's
going to be an engineering manual for the Commission.
Nevertheless, it did seem to have some useful suggestions.
Agent Wagner, you want to comment on that
document? You probably reviewed it more closely than I did.
>> Yeah, I can just explain
it. It was just basically New Hampshire has a
clause
requiring a buffer on the shoreline.
So if you want to construct any kind of beach, you have to use what's called a perch beach,
is what they what they recommend.
So you basically put,
it's basically it's kind of like this, you'd have a stone wall,
and then you'd have,
you know, some kind of retaining wall
between
the beach and the
lakeshore, and then you'd have like some stairs or something in New Hampshire, they have a, you know, an actual buffer zone. So the wall would be in a few feet back from the
from the actual lakeshore,
and then you'd depending
on the topography, you'd have, you know, maybe a drainage swale on the uphill side of the beach to prevent erosion.
Mr. McCullough's
property is pretty
flat, so I can't see a lot of erosion potential from the uphill side.
But you know, it could incorporate
something like that into the design.
But basically, yeah, the the
New Hampshire recommends
the Perch Beach because it it preserves the natural shoreline and allows people to enjoy their property.
So that's
what the document was about.
Okay.
>> Yeah. I guess I would only ask if if you guys
in your free time, like everybody has a lot of free time, but if you take a look at that and there's something that really stands out as a showstopper for you before I get too far into
the planning and stuff like that,
or
during the planning,
call that out as opposed to, I don't know,
later in the process, I guess earlier rather than later.
>> That's quite reasonable. I think we'll make that effort. And again, communication with, Agent Wagner,
during the planning process is going to be very valuable.
Yes, I found,
Agent Wagner to be very helpful.
>> Okay,
listen, if we have no further
questions or comments, we can't obviously act on this application.
We're
in agreement on
the sidewalk and
try to get a better understanding
of the
project impact
at that time.
Okay. I
would like to move on in our agenda
in the interest of time. Before we do that, Chairman Bill, one I
>> of the options is, because the project
is
going to end up being so different,
is the applicant could pull the current application
so that we don't have to worry about the maximum
time limit before
the
application gets approved without action from the commission.
I don't know that we're going to be in a spot to vote on it at the next meeting
even.
In the next meeting would be the absolute
end date. It's the day before our max
allowed time limit.
>> It can be
extended with the applicant's consent. You can extend it, I think, to sixty five days from there. The applicant has to agree to
the extension.
>> But
I do also
think that
the current application
isn't at all what we're going to be
looking at, and so it might be cleaner just to pull this application and submit
one that actually addresses what it is the applicant wants to do.
>> Does that mean I have to pay for another application?
>> I would say no, but I'm not sure. No, no, it's not our intention that it should be a
new app, but a revised application,
you know,
revised application form attachments and so forth,
all in one package, I think, what we're really looking for here,
so that we're essentially all on the same page with the
updated
and, you know, extensively modified
proposal.
>> Yeah, so basically,
you know,
say,
you know, we're going to not even talk about the
>> Yeah, scratch the sand beach entirely.
That's not going to happen. We know that because Alma,
you know, that is to say sand on the lake bed.
Right. That is the, and you're already under
caution
to
get that sand off of the lake bed. Right, right. As soon as possible, you know. So,
you know, that would,
again, the proposal
for what you actually intend to do
would be the appropriate revision
rather
than, you know, continuing
to submit
appendices
or addendums.
>> Okay. And I'll I'll work with Joe,
I guess, that's something we can
work together on again.
I I can do get whatever
we got. I just don't know what forms to put it on.
>> Yeah. I don't I don't know. I think that might get
tricky because you have the the public review,
you were to rescind your application and then reapply next month, it would
that would put you into
March before you could even get any approval.
I I
don't know. I I don't see I
don't see any benefit to to doing it that way.
I think
just revising it like like any other application as you go along, which is kind of the purpose of this whole process is is I
don't know, I think it's working right now because we're we're coming up with with better a better plan as the application progresses through this process.
Rather than just getting it right the first time, which, you know, doesn't happen too often.
Basically, it would be your choice whether or not to resend the application or not. You could, you know, you could you
could keep it here,
the commission could take a vote, or you could decide to extend it next month.
But I think,
time wise, I think it it wouldn't make any sense to do it that way.
That's just my thought.
>> Well, yeah.
We're not I don't think we need a new application number, as it were, a new clock ticking,
because
it would, as H. Wagner
points out,
put you into a situation
where you really couldn't hope to get approval
or any work done,
within the timeframe that's open.
So,
again, I think that the main point here is to make sure that we're all clear
about exactly what is being proposed
in the application.
>> Well,
well, and that's part of what the sidewalk's gonna do. I think we've we've
beaten a proverbial dead horse here a little bit. I think we know
it's clear to me.
I don't know if there's
I don't know where the confusion is.
If there's,
you know,
letter or another
attempt to
document
what we're
doing.
I mean, there was a few bullet points there. Was
you guys tell me.
I just assumed I want
want it to be easy,
as easy as possible. I don't want to make it harder on myself or you guys.
>> My concern about starting the application over again was
strictly
twofold.
One was
time limits
that
we're up against.
I didn't even mention
the option that we could vote on the current application to disapprove it and start the clock over that way because that's not conducive to
working with you in the manner that we
are to come up with a better product.
The other thing that I have seen is that when we go back years from now and try and you'll pull the file and understand what we did,
records haven't always been very clear that way. And so one of the things I'm trying to do is make our records better for those who come after us to understand what actually happened.
And if Agent Wagner is happy with
the way it's going,
I just want, you know, when we approve a plan that it's crystal clear what we're really approving,
because
sometimes
there's some confusion on that.
>> All this
revised stuff is all dated January
10.
So there's two,
There's a existing conditions map that I submitted. There's Gary's
map of his proposed
activities,
all dated January 10, and then there's the description of the project that's dated January 10. And then
if there's any more revisions,
would just the date would be reflected
in the approval motion. So you, you know, make
an approval motion to approve
the revised,
you know,
January 10, or whatever date
it happens to be at that point.
And that would be reflected in the permit. So you could go back in the files in the future, and you could see
a copy of the permit
that states which
set of maps and which project description
is actually approved.
I have
have run into that problem in the past, Jen. I've been trying to to make sure that the stuff I put in there is somebody
that can go can go back and if I dropped in, figure out what what was going on there. So
>> I think with having all the files
online
and
organized
by application number and so forth, there's been a great deal of progress
in making it easier to find the information we need. And so keeping track of the revision dates,
is
very helpful,
in tracking,
the application process.
For example, when went through the
bridge,
not the
Wellman Crossing permit process with extensive
revisions of Full Farms Road and so forth.
So, I think we can handle it basically,
and I think that we should continue
with the existing
permit.
And again,
understanding
that if we run up against the deadline, we're going to be asking the applicant for
the
extension
that's permitted
or the extension of the permit application.
Okay. Well, with that, I'd really like to move on
to our
next item on the agenda.
We have a,
let's see now,
2128.
It's a
application for permit for wetlands
crossings
for purposes of logging
activity.
We had the sidewalk,
and commissioners
were able to
see the
locations,
and in fact, some of the,
as it were, history
of logging on the site,
where
previously corduroy had been used for stream crossing
and
was still sort of
embedded
in the lake, or not the lake, but stream
bed,
and
where they proposed to put a,
what's it called, portable
bridge,
timbers crossing
that little arm of
Staddle Brook.
Let's see, we have anyone
representing
the applicant
on the call tonight?
I
don't see one. I think that,
if I recall, at
the sidewalk,
Mr. Dubois
I can't remember the pronunciation
did not intend to
be at this meeting.
Is that a recollection,
Agent Wagner?
>> Yeah, that's what he told me. He had talked to you about it
at the sidewalk. I don't I don't know if I was there. I think I'd gone back to take pictures or something. Okay.
>> Well, in any case, we have the application,
and
for
in order to move forward on it, I'm going to make a motion
to approve
the permit application
ask for, with of course standard conditions,
and ask
for a second to that motion.
I'll
second. Okay,
>> so moved and seconded.
Okay, everybody had a chance to take a look at the pictures that Agent Wagner posted for
refreshing our memory. Any
questions or comments
about the application?
Mr. Munro?
>> Yeah,
I did look at that
video with the
bridge up in Vermont.
And it appears that the bridge just
spans the entire stream. Is that what his plan is too?
Do you know?
That was my impression.
Any other?
Yeah, I agree
>> with that impression.
Know, I think
I asked him if there were going to be any stanchions going down into the screen to support the bridge in the center,
and he said no.
Good.
Excuse me.
>> Well, if it's gonna span that that area that he brought it brought us to there, that
would be a huge improvement over what happened there the last time.
>> Indeed,
best management practices for logging have
advanced
over the past twenty, thirty years.
Okay, any other questions or comments?
Mr. Larson, do you have any?
I'm all set.
>> Chairman Elliot? Yeah. Chairman, this is Hank from the Conservation Commission. Sure, but I just ask a
question.
Sure, regarding it. Do
>> you recall if there is
a planned use of siltation fencing for the project?
>> No,
it was I
don't believe it was specified. AJ Wagner, do you have any recollection? Mine is that
there were no other
specific
erosion controls or anything like that
on that project. I don't recall that they were
We certainly hadn't seen that in any of the previous logging projects that I'm aware of.
>> Okay, good. I just wanted to be clear out. Just check on that because I was concerned that if it was planned because of the timing with
amphibian migrations coming up for the spring, but if it's not being used, that's perfect. Fine. Okay.
>> Yeah. Think they're actually they're hoping to start
sometime this week, so
it should be
>> be done before Conditions
are pretty good right now.
Okay, so if there are no further questions or comments, I'll call for a vote on the
motion.
Commissioner
Larson?
Aye.
Commissioner Monroe?
>> And I also vote aye, so the motion carries three zero. Joe,
you can go ahead and issue the permit,
and
good luck to them.
Okay,
next item on the agenda.
Under new business,
we have IWWC2129
for
activity in the Upland Review area
for a project.
Guess the official address is on Lake Road
And
Commercial Development and so forth.
We
have a,
of course,
highly detailed application,
and I will ask for
the representative
of the agent or the owners
or agents or whoever, would that be Jessica Bates
of Thank BL
you.
If you could
sort of clue us in on the little bitty part of the project that actually
is
on an upland review area
and what the potential impacts might be there.
>> Definitely.
If it's okay with the Commission, I would like to share my screen just so I can kind of show you.
Otherwise, I'm going to talk with my hands. So either you can see me talk with my hands or you can look at the plan. Yeah,
>> board clerk who is administering the meeting should be able to arrange for you to share screen.
>> Okay. You should be able to, Jessica. Just let me know if you can.
>> Okay. Thank you. So
this is the site plan.
First of all, hi. My name is Jessica Bates. I'm a professional engineer. I work for BL companies.
My office is in Hartford, Connecticut.
We're here to discuss the application at 580
Lake Road.
It's at the intersection of Lake Road and Route 6
right in front of Ben Franklin Plumbing Supplies.
It is in the Upland Review area, as
Mr. Chairman said,
due to the proximity to Chaney Brook.
Chaney Brook is on this
plan right here, is actually pointing down. So, Chaney Brook on the plan is on the left side of the screen across
Lake Road from the application site.
The approximate high water of Cheney Brook is this dark, like,
kind of
jagged line,
and the Upland Review area is this green line that goes kind of halfway through the building and through part of the parking lot.
As I said previously,
the wetland is on the other side of the road from the application site, and the topography of this site all drains kind of from the
upper left hand side of the screen to the lower
right hand side of the screen. There is a culvert oops, I'm gonna move my hatching
There is a culvert beneath Route 6 that this site entirely drains to, and there is absolutely no water or anything that is going towards water sediment silt or anything of that nature that could get into Chaneybrook as a result of the construction activities on this site.
Even the driveway and everything else, that part of Lake Road is actually draining towards Route 6 and the cross culvert that goes beneath Route 6.
This site in general ranges in topography from roughly two ninety nine here to
approximately two ninety two in this location.
It is zoned
industrial.
Retail sales is allowed.
There's no FEMA floodplain on this site.
The
application is for a 10,640
square foot building
with 35 parking spaces. We are calling for some parking spaces to be regular, bituminous
asphalt
and some parking spaces to be pervious asphalt.
There are two driveway
to this parking to this lot. One would be from Route 6 and one would be from Lake Road.
That is under review currently by the Connecticut Department of Transportation.
The Upland Review Area, as I said previously, falls on-site,
but there's no significant work in the Upland Review Area, and there would be no effects to the wetlands
due to this
proposed
construction site.
The utility is on-site. Everything is available readily electric, telephone is in Route 6.
We would have a septic system,
which is under review by the health department as we speak now,
and the well would be required, and there would be a Connecticut Department of Health transient non community well on-site.
The photometrics for the site are LED, dark sky compliant,
full cutoff light fixtures.
There is an increase in impervious.
Obviously, this is right now a maintained lawn, so any impervious would automatically be an increase in impervious.
To mitigate the effects of the increase in impervious, we have a closed drainage system that will have sumps
beneath the outlets,
hoods to catch floatables and debris,
hydrodynamic separators for total suspended solids and removal
for the water quality flow,
and leaching underground chambers, concrete chambers on this site to mitigate the pre post effect of
impervious cover
on this site.
Erosion control, we are in full compliance with the Connecticut erosion control manual,
and we are in compliance with
the 2,002
stormwater quality manual.
Landscaping has a variety of trees and shrubs,
grasses that really produces an aesthetically pleasing site from both Lake Road and Route 6.
Really, that's kind of a general overview of the site itself.
In conclusion, we're saying we really have no significant
impacts in the Upland Review area, and there will be no adverse effects on the wetland system that is across
Lake Road from the application site.
I think you're muted, Mr. I
think.
>> Sorry.
I'll thank
engineer Bates for a
concise
and
informative presentation,
and I'll ask if any of the commissioners have any specific questions
regarding the project.
>> We can talk more about it if you want. I have one question,
>> and that is
I am under the impression
that our zoning agent is discussed with somebody from your company, I don't know who,
about the fact that
sidewalks will be required to be put in
the upland review area. And so while I don't think that that will have any detrimental effect on anything,
it would preclude us from having to come back to wetlands if we made sure that the sidewalks
were shown on the drawing that
wetlands will
>> take action. Yeah, if could
make that a condition of approval, we can definitely add that. We
would put it on the side of the street and pitch it towards the road, it really still would have no adverse effects on the wetlands on the other side of the street.
It wouldn't change our stormwater management design. It's very, very minimal increase in impervious cover based on the entire site in and of itself. So, yeah, we have no problems adding the sidewalks to the site, and we would appreciate the opportunity to do that as a condition of approval.
>> Okay.
Commissioner Liesing, you were referring to a that would be a zoning condition
as opposed to a
building permit condition.
It wouldn't be something that would be imposed by the IWWC.
We just want to make sure that
when we do
and we won't be, of course,
considering this application for approval tonight, but when we do, we want to make sure that what we have is on the same page
as what Commissioner Larson's.
>> I do think it would be appropriate
to have it as a condition of approval for the Inland Wetlands
decision
because
that way, there can be no question of the fact that that was
addressed
by the Inland Wetlands Commission and it won't require
the drawing to come back to wetlands again
when sidewalks get added. If we recognize that there's going be a plan for sidewalks, I think that might be better for us in the long run.
>> Okay, so that's a modification you'd like to see in the application prior to
our further consideration of it. Again, that would be our next meeting.
>> But if
they can update the drawings before then, that would be great. But if not,
you know, when we approve,
we make motions to approve things, it has conditions of approval and to have listed
the recognition that sidewalks will be included in the upland review area on the final plan,
I think that
covers as well.
>> And to get the plans in in time to be reviewed by the Commission prior to the next meeting,
what would be the
deadline for that? If you tell me it's yesterday,
it'll be a I'm
good. I'm not that good.
>> Well, I thought with CAD you could do things, you know. It's a couple clicks. A click of the switch, right? Yeah,
we should be so lucky. No, our next meeting is not won't be until February 6, and I think that, you know, if we get materials
within a week of the meeting, that's ample time for
>> us That's to the best I can do. Okay.
Yeah, it just it's the
printing and everything else, it takes some time, so I just wanted to make sure
we had a couple of days to be able to put them on plans, print them, and get them back to you guys. Right.
>> I guess we're still having to deal with paper in some respects.
Always.
Forever.
>> Okay, any other questions or comments?
Okay.
You know, in a way, this is being
an upland review project, we could actually
leave this for agent approval. But I think that the extent of the project is such that probably be better if the whole commission,
such as it is,
has review
over the application.
Okay?
>> So So just so I'm clear, is this going to be just voted on on the next meeting, or is it a public hearing for the next meeting?
>> Well, that's a good point. I'm getting the sense that we don't regard this as having a significant impact,
and therefore, we don't really need to have a hearing
on the wetlands
aspect
of the application.
And,
you know,
I can't speak for Planning and Zoning Commission, although
Commissioner Larsen certainly could.
I'm not sure whether
a public hearing would be anticipated
for
an application of this scope.
>> But again, I don't see I just meant under this commission, is the next meeting going to be a public hearing
or not? I don't think I didn't mean under planning and zoning, just meant under planning and No, no, no. Meant the
>> if there were going to be a planning and zoning, we'd probably want to get our act on the same page.
I don't see a need for hearing
for this application
for this commission.
Okay.
>> Unless I hear otherwise from my commissioners.
And again, that question there is that
it doesn't have
a significant
impact
on the associated weapons.
And
again, based on the sense that it won't,
there is no need for a public hearing on the wetlands
aspect.
I agree with that.
>> Okay.
So
if we, again, if we have a general sense of the project,
and especially it's a wetlands
aspect,
and
that we won't require a public hearing, and we should be able to act on the application
at our next meeting,
again, provided we get the updated
revisions
associated with the need
for a sidewalk.
Hey, the skateboarders have got to go someplace, right?
Yes. Okay.
So any other questions or comments on
the proposal,
on the application?
If
not, we'll move on to our remaining agenda.
And again, thank Engineer Bates, and you may be excused
from the meeting.
>> From the classroom? Yes.
Thank you very much. Have a great night. Okay, good night. Bye.
>> Okay,
let me find the agenda again here on my screen.
Right, yeah, other business.
And finally, the people who have been hanging in there all this time waiting for their moment to arrive,
the Conservation Commission, as we recall,
initiated
an inventory of vernal pools
in town of Andover, and last year we got an excellent report on
activities of UConn students who applied
their
geospatial
and GIS
skills
to identify potential
goals. And now, our Conservation Commission,
with our
support,
wants to move it forward. So, I'm going to ask Hank Brunner,
representing the Conservation Commission, to tell us what's coming up next.
>> Thank you, Cherimina Elliott. And Abby, if I could share screen?
>> Yep. I just need you to call host who should be able to. Let me know if you can't. Alright. Hold on.
>> Let's see if I can
call up this PowerPoint real quick.
Where'd it go? There it goes.
>> You guys see that?
I've got a blank screen that says Hank Greener has started. There we go. There you go. Alright, everybody sees the map of Andover. Hopefully we recognize that boundaries of the town
and all those blue dots. If you remember, this is where we last left off. These were the potential vertical pools that were mapped working with the Yukon students that
Chairman Elliott mentioned.
And just a reminder that their potential vertical pools at this point, because really
what we need to do is be able to collect some biological data to confirm whether they are in fact functioning as vertical pools, requires
the presence of certain
obligate species.
Let me put this in
slide mode here to make it a little easier actually just go to this. So
what we've done in the next step is really to do is to look at.
Doing those biological surveys so obviously the pools are on a variety of parcel some are public and some are private.
We did a cross reference of the potential pools
in the using the GIS mapping
and we came across with of the 183 pools potential pools that were mapped 78%
of them are on private land
and 22%
of them are on public land.
The public lands, as you know, you know we have town land. Have some land trust property. We have some large tracts of state land and Bishop Swamp Wildlife Management area
portions in Nathan Hale State Forest,
but the majority are on private land, which is typical.
Number of pools for parcel also I thought it would be interesting to look at is they can range anywhere from on private land one to 15 pools per parcel and on public land one to 21 pools for parcel.
We identified
landowners associated with those private lands
that we would need to request permission from. We
went back and over the past week actually several members of the Commission look through the property records
in town to confirm
because they're more up to date and we're able to identify
confirm
59 of those and 59 addresses.
So
our next up what we'd like to do and want to bring to the Commission is we prepared a letter,
a final draft letter for your review.
Included by agent Wagner in the package
for review.
And
approval
because we'd like to be able to send that out as early as next week,
no later than
first week of February
to
attempt to get landowner permission
to do surveys
later in the spring.
Does everybody have that a copy of that letter?
>> Right, the updated letter that Hank referring to was sent
out,
let's see now,
on the seventh.
I have an email,
and it
I
had a little bit of input into drafting that letter,
in particular in volunteering
the
Inland Wild And Water Courses Commission
email
address
through the town of Andover
Outlook
email server,
so we have a quote official
email address
for that correspondence.
>> And the letter is really two parts. The first part is sort of the introduction to the landowner and what this project is.
And then the second part is the check basically a checkoff sheet that would be returned back to
Chairman Elliott mentioned to the official
location either via mail or email. Those
we would use to tabulate
the sites where we would be able to provide access.
>> Hank, I would offer that I did see the letter, I did read the letter,
but I didn't recognize
that I should be reading it with the critical eye to give you feedback on it. I know I got the point across, I thought it was very good,
but I didn't scrutinize it
carefully,
if you would.
>> Take a minute because I'm going to ask for approval
to
send that letter
since it is at least partly under our aegis.
Again, although this is essentially a conservation commission activity, it's certainly one that we support
since the information is
useful
from a
wellness regulation
point of view,
knowing that it's there
will
certainly help guide
activities.
And I think that, again,
the idea of having,
well, at least get one
or possibly two
attempts at getting a letter out and getting that and giving it time for response
means that
the letter, the first letter at least, will have to be sent. And as Sank says, very soon,
the window of opportunity
is fairly narrow for actually identifying and characterizing
actual vernal pools.
I will say that again, having had input into the letter, I'm quite satisfied with its content.
>> I have a question.
Bill Monroe.
I
see it says
each
Vernell pool
sampling should take
thirty to sixty minutes
and up to two surveys will be conducted per pool. Mhmm.
Now how
is this two surveys?
I mean,
I'm looking at it from the homeowners,
private
property owners, you know, I mean, it's it's two two surveys that they're just going to have two surveys. These people are going to be
Volunteers are going to be on their property just.
Just twice and
and how much.
Amount of time would that be like?
It like within five years or within no one?
>> Yeah, it there there would be two surveys. One ideally would be and it depends a little bit the timing of when the amphibian season breaks,
but typically one would be in March and one would be in April.
And this each each one of those surveys they would be on the property for thirty to sixty minutes. So there would be two surveys this spring.
They would all be completed by
certainly by the end of May mid to the end of May,
depending on how the season falls. But generally, the surveys will occur between March and May.
Okay.
Thank you.
Answered my question.
Now, it looks like George might have left us.
Who's George?
>> I don't see him on the list.
Maybe he'll come back.
Should we text him?
>> Hey, Ken. I don't have his phone number,
but if you have one.
Let's see.
>> I found his phone number. I'll give him a call if no one else is yet.
>> Yeah. I haven't yeah. I was looking for his number. Okay. Yep. I'll, give him a call. Hold on.
Thanks, Abby.
Hello?
Hello, George.
>> Hi, Abby.
I'm
sitting here looking at a Zoom screen that's telling me
to,
well, first of all, I'll try to join. I got booted out. I don't know what happened.
I'm trying again now, but it does not seem to want I don't seem to be getting a connection.
And
I have no idea why because my Wi Fi and
Ethernet are both active.
So
are others
still in the meeting and active?
>> Yep. We're all here. I'll I'll investigate to see if I can get to the root of it, but, your phone works for now.
>> Okay.
It's pretty hard to keep track of what's going on just by phone,
and I'll hope that the connection will be restored.
How
do I
get what others are saying? Can you patch me into that?
>> I think everyone can speak. I can hear you, George. Can you hear me? Yeah.
You should be able to hear us.
>> Okay,
I can can hear you, Judd, and
I hope
that we can proceed this way. As I said, it's really strange
that I can't get the connection. I may just
while we're talking, I'm I'm gonna quit
and try starting over again. That sometimes does more than anything else.
Okay. I'm not getting anywhere with trying to restart Zoom.
Just got a spinning wheel that says connecting.
So,
again, question is, are we in a will
we be in a position?
Can we go ahead and approve
the letter
being sent
to
property owners
regarding the Vernal Pool
survey.
I think we hear from
Commissioner Monroe's comment
might be well to just add
that this might occur in March and April.
So other than that,
are there any
suggestions?
I have no other comments.
>> Okay.
Once again, I have absolutely no idea why
I can't get on to the Zoom meeting from my laptop here.
I have one more bright idea. I may be able to do it from my desktop
and we'll try that.
But I don't have a lot of hope.
Especially since the link from the PDF file doesn't seem to be working.
>> I just sent you a new invite to the
IWWC
chair email if that's helpful.
>> Okay.
I'll, certainly give that a try. Why am I getting duck duck go go coming up here?
Okay.
I'll see if Outlook will let me in.
If I look, we'll ever load.
Okay. Got the link.
Waiting for it to open.
Looks like we got you.
>> There we go. You want me both? Okay.
How about that?
I'll, ring off of the phone then.
>> Okay. Oddly enough, can anybody hear me?
Jed, you're the only person I can see.
Can you raise your hand or I
can hear you.
Okay.
I don't see myself.
I see you.
So we're looking at just a marginal improvement.
They said the only
>> Okay, now I can see other participants
and myself.
Okay, we're making progress here.
So where were we when I got
booted out?
>> I think we were just looking. I don't know if you want a motion or just a consensus that
the letter is ready to send out.
Okay. Participants
in the meeting hear me? Yes.
Yes. Yes.
>> Okay,
I think we have communication.
Again, I'm switching platforms
here, so it's a little awkward.
I now have
a panel with participants
and
Hank's
screen with the PowerPoint presentation.
And again, we have discussion of the
proposed
letter
to be sent to landowners.
We have
proposed modification of the letter to
indicate at least the
window
of dates that would be
relevant for
the surveys.
And
any other
comments,
suggestions?
Okay, then. With that modification,
I would like to move that the commission approve
sending that letter.
I'll second.
>> Thank you. So, motion and second to approve sending the letter.
And
again, by roll call, Commissioner Larson?
Aye.
Commissioner Monroe?
>> And I also vote aye, so the motion carries three-zero-zero.
Hank, I think you can run through the
Conservation Commission
to have a little detail added.
And Yep.
>> We'll look forward to getting some responses.
Yep. At least from a few of the landowners in contact.
Yeah. And hopefully 20%. That's what
is typical. Okay.
>> Thank you. So one last a fair amount of activity. That could be a lot of pools to sleep.
>> Yeah. Well, we'll see.
We'll see.
So,
so just a quick slide, the next steps then. Will the landowner mailing will occur January through early April. We'll get that out and thank you for your approval and support of the project.
We
also are scheduling, just to make you aware, a public program to promote awareness at the library on February 23.
That's more of a general introduction to virtual pools. All
Wetlands Commission members are more than welcome to attend that if you want to find out a little bit more.
And then on April 9 through the sixteenth waiting to confirm the date on that with amy at the library
will do a field experience to a pool
that.
Carrie Crompton and I identified and looked at for training that's behind the recreational fields. There's actually a couple pools there. So
we'll do a field
and that's a Saturday. We'll do a field program to give folks a chance to
sort of explore a vertical pool and see a little bit about the life in the pool. And then we'll move into volunteer recruitment.
Beginning in February actually,
and then with the training probably toward the end of February or early March of the volunteers
on the techniques and what needs to be done for the for the collecting the data, And then the verbal pool surveys themselves will occur March through May.
>> Good.
Well, again,
good luck recruiting volunteers.
I'm there'll be some community interest.
>> Yeah. Of course, if any members of the commission are interested in volunteering, they'd be more than welcome.
>> Going to say we would be encouraged,
as commissioners,
and
I would,
on a household basis, expect also to be encouraged
to
participate
in this conservation
commission activity.
Okay?
>> Well, thanks a lot, Hank. I'm really sorry for all the No, that's okay. That's the world we live in today with technology.
We've all had our share of
dealing with workarounds.
>> Yeah, indeed.
Good.
Just thought I've got two screens to work with.
So
with that, I guess we can move on to the
other item that we have in other business, which is
the
revised regulations.
You'll recall from our last meeting,
we are obliged
to hold a hearing
before we can adopt those regulations
since we're really not
proposing anything substantively new. You know, we're not coming up with some radical
new regulations
for Andover.
We're just incorporating
updates
to the model regulations from DEEP.
I don't anticipate
a whole lot of
discussion, you know, a lot to hear in a hearing.
And what I would like to propose then is that we simply schedule a hearing
prior
to a regular meeting,
And that way we can hold a hearing, and then during a regular meeting,
we can discuss and hopefully vote
to approve
the updated regulations.
Commissioners,
do you have any thoughts on that matter?
Sounds good to me. Okay.
Commissioner Munro?
Same here. Okay.
>> And then we got to figure out a time. I'm thinking that in order to allow plenty of time for
required notification,
we do have toI
don't remember the exact dates myself, but I know that, you know, we have deadlines in terms of public notice. We'll probably have to put in I'm sure we'll have to put a notice in the River East
at
some interval before
the hearing. You know, there has to be adequate public notice.
So, I'm thinking that the
regular meeting in March,
would be an appropriate time,
to schedule that hearing.
And
I'm pulling back my calendar just to double check. Yeah, the
first
Monday of March
is March
7,
so our regular meeting
would normally be at 7PM.
We could schedule for the hearing for 7PM
and the hearing
to follow I mean, excuse me, the regular meeting to follow the hearing at seven
So, if that's
copacetic,
we can, I guess, can adopt that by unanimous consent
and
pencil it in our calendars?
And,
Agent Wagner, I'll ask you to,
attend to the details of
posting the warning and all of that for a public hearing
regarding the updated or the revised
regulations.
The current regulations, of course, are posted on our website.
We could probably post the
revised regulations
as well.
If you don't have them in PDF format,
I do. I've got all the original
documents
that were
created during the process.
>> Yeah. Probably just to make sure I got the right version to post.
If you could send me Yeah. Okay.
I'll I'll I'll do that. We got some time.
>> George, do we need a motion to schedule the public hearing?
>> Yeah, we could do it formally.
And do you want to make that motion?
>> I make a motion that we hold a public hearing 07:00 on March 7 for the purpose of discussing the
changes to the inland wetlands regulations.
I'll second that.
>> Alright, motion is second.
Vote on the motion by Commissioner Lawson?
Aye.
Commissioner Monroe?
And I also vote aye, so the motion carries three-zero-zero.
So, we'll be good to go.
With that, we can move on to the next item of our agenda,
which would be
should we go to calendar? Okay.
Yeah. We got any enforcement actions or agent report.
>> Actually, it's been a
quiet month, so no no Christmas time enforcement actions.
I can continue to agent report.
I didn't have any
any applications or approvals,
in December.
>> Indeed So. A quiet month.
Okay.
Maybe it'll get busier when things pick up in the spring. Okay,
so thanks for that input.
>> Then moving on with the agenda. We'll move on, George. I did have one question for our agent.
You been out to
see the subdivision on Pine Ridge Drive
recently.
And the reason I asked the question is I think they are clearing the lot out there
and I don't know exactly
how they're getting
the cleared trees
across the wetlands.
And there was a discussion that they were all going to be stockpiled out there,
but
I just, you know,
I think it would be worth
putting your eyes on the target and see what's actually going on with respect to,
you know,
that happening. I don't know if they're going to leave everything back there or how they get it across the wetlands to even do the cutting down out there.
The bridge certainly isn't in place to go across the wetlands at this point.
>> Yeah. From a I did visit it. I forget what the exact date was, but
Jim Halsey and me and
Eric Lteska and George Korea were out there
probably a few weeks ago, maybe two or three weeks ago.
And we walked,
from the old farm's
side.
And that's where
at that time, that's where the work was going on, and they were actually working from from that way, and there was a
like an old road that they're
seem like at that time, they're they're doing the tree clearing from
all from that part from the old driveway that was in
from the previous owner. And he was working from that, working his way towards
the wetland crossing from
from that direction. But at that time, they're just clearing,
like, opening up that road again and working from there. But I'll definitely
swing by there see
see what's going on. Keep an eye on it.
Thank you.
>> Any other questions or
comments for our
agent?
Okay, then as I say, moving on with the agenda. Our next regular meeting will be Monday, February 7,
same time, same virtual place,
and hopefully we'll fuel problems next time.
And
with that,
we come to the final item
on the agenda,
namely adjournment.
With
no objection,
we may adjourn by unanimous
consent.
Seems to be okay.
So, I will consider the meeting adjourned
at 09:05PM.
Well, thanks all for your patience, and
we have a
wonderful month, and hope that it warms up in time for our site walk.
I look forward to seeing you all then.
Until then, we can click on the little red button that says leave.
Bye bye. Good night, everyone. Hey, everybody. Bye.